Finding Aid for Dance Gallery Foundation records, 1980-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dance Gallery Foundation records 1980-2008, 1993-2008
Dance Gallery Foundation.
1 oversize boxes
5.5 linear feet
2008093 Bp2
The records in this collection relate to the Peter Sparling Dance Company (PSDC) and the Dance Gallery Studio. The Dance Gallery Foundation was founded in 1984 and sponsored three professional modern dance companies during its history; J Parker Copley Dance Company (1986-1990); Dance Gallery with Alan Lommasson (1990-1991) and the Peter Sparling Dance Company with Artistic Director Peter Sparling (1993-2008). The Dance Gallery Studio closed its doors in August 2008. The records in this collection date primarily from 1993, although the collection does also include some material from Sparling's work in the 1980s. Records in the collection include promotional materials, photographs, video tapes, class schedules, administrative files, programs, production notes, and press clippings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Accession received through Peter Sparling. (Donor no 10092 ) in 2008
Periodic additions to the records expected.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Dance Gallery Foundation began in 1984 and served as the umbrella organization for three modern dance companies in its twenty-four year history; J Parker Copley Dance Company (1986-1990); Dance Gallery with Alan Lommasson (1990-1991), and the Peter Sparling Dance Company with Artistic Director Peter Sparling (1993-2008).
Sparling began the Peter Sparling Dance Company (PSDC) as a nonprofit company, and the Dance Gallery Studio as a not-for-profit dance studio, under the auspices of the Dance Gallery Foundation in 1993. Sparling, Professor and Chair in the University of Michigan Dance Department, danced with the Jose Limon and Martha Graham Dance Companies and is experienced in dance instruction and choreography. Sparling has borrowed from Graham and Limon to create his own innovative and sensuous style of choreography.
The Company's productions included text and musical scores, as well as classical and popular music. The PSDC sought to use modern dance to express "human experience from the comic, tragic, and sublime, to the ecstatic, ethereal, and extraordinary." During Sparling's tenure as Artistic Director, the PSDC repertory included newly choreographed dances to classical works such as Gluck's Orfeo ed Euridice, Vivaldi's The Four Seasons, Schubert's Nacht und Traume, Handel's "Ombra mai fu" from Serse and "Lascia ch'io pianga" from Rinaldo, Chopin's Nocturnes and Bach's Sonata No. 3 in C Major for Unaccompanied Violin. The Company also featured contemporary works choreographed by Sparling, including productions such as Dances to Ives, The End of Shame, Possible Dances, Traffic!, Peninsula, and Chronicles and Small Comforts.
In addition to supporting the Peter Sparling Dance Company, the Dance Gallery Foundation ran and funded the Dance Gallery Studio. The studio offered adult and children's classes and workshops in modern, ballet, jazz, creative movement, contact, improvisation, hip-hop, Pilates, yoga, Tai Chi, Eurythmy, Brazilian dance, Alexander Technique, and Feldenkrais. Originally housed in Ann Arbor's Technology Center, the Dance Gallery Foundation moved to the former Ann Arbor Ball Bearing Factory in 2003, converting the former industrial space into a 5,000 square foot studio designed to accommodate dance classes, dance company rehearsals, and community outreach programming.
In addition to promoting its own company and studio, the Dance Gallery Foundation partnered with community groups and educational organizations (from elementary and high schools, to community colleges and universities) to host free or low cost workshops, educational outreach programs, lectures, and master classes.
The Dance Gallery Foundation sought financial support from a variety of sources including class fees, gifts, performance booking fees, residencies, lecture demonstrations, master classes, and grants and awards. Over the years, the Foundation also hosted a number of benefit performances and receptions in Ann Arbor, such as a series at the Earle Restaurant, designed to support the Dance Company and the Foundation. However, in August 2008, due to inadequate funding, the Dance Gallery Studio closed and the Peter Sparling Dance Company lost its permanent home. In the wake of the Studio's closing, the Dance Company planned to operate on a case-by-case basis.
The Dance gallery Foundation records measure 5.25 linear feet, including oversized materials, and date from, 1980 to 2008, with the majority of the records from the period 1993-2007. The records are primarily comprised of press clippings, programs, promotional materials, administrative files, photographs, and video, and are arranged into ten series: Administrative; Bookings; Dance Gallery Studio; Development; Press Clippings; Productions; Programs; Promotional Materials; Audio-Visual Materials, and Website.
Subjects:
Dance Gallery Studio.; Peter Sparling Dance Company.; Choreographers.; Dancers.; Dance--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Modern Dance.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dance Gallery Studio.; Peter Sparling Dance Company.; Choreographers.; Dancers.; Dance--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Modern Dance.; Sparling, Peter, 1951-; Sparling, Peter, 1951-, Performances.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative 1994-2006
  The Administrative series, 1994-2006 (1.25 linear ft.), contains general administrative notes and correspondence regarding productions and staffing, advertising plans, and copies of the Dance Gallery Studio's quarterly newsletter.
  - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Advertising (Box 1)
  - Files by Year
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters 1995-2005 (Box 2)
- Bookings 1999-2006
  Materials in the Bookings series, 1999-2006 (0.2 linear ft.), include information on bookings details, solicitations, and conferences, as well as plans for bookings with the Michigan Humanities Council, the Michigan Presenters Network, and the Ohio Presenters Network.
  - General (Box 2)
  - Solicitations (Box 2)
  - Conferences (Box 2)
  - Michigan Humanities Council (Box 2)
  - Michigan Presenters Network (Box 2)
  - Ohio Arts Presenters Network (Box 2)
- Dance Gallery Studio
  The Dance Gallery Studio series, 1988-2003 (0.1 linear ft.), includes class and workshops schedules and announcements for the Studio's adult, children's, and master classes in ballet, modern, jazz, pilates, Feldenkrais, creative movement, Latin/Swing, yoga, Tai Chi, contact, hip-hop, and ballroom dancing.
  - Class Schedules (Box 2)
  - Workshops (Box 2)
- Development
  The Development series, 1990-2005 (0.1 linear ft.), contains records documenting the Dance Gallery Foundation's fundraising activities. The series includes event invitations, donor letters and solicitations, and grant applications, as well as information on corporate and individual donors.
  - Events (Box 2)
  - Grants (Box 2)
  - Friends & Director's Circle (Box 2)
- Press Clippings
  The Press Clippings series, 1980-2007 (.25 linear ft.), contains press clippings, publicity notices, event announcements, and performance reviews for the Peter Sparling Dance Company and the Dance Gallery Studio. The clippings are primarily from The Ann Arbor News, the Detroit Free Press, and Current. However there are also clippings from The New York Times and Dance World.
  - 1980-1992 (Box 2)
  - 1993 (Box 2)
  - 1994 (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996 (Box 2)
  - 1997 (Box 2)
  - 1998 (Box 2)
  - 1999 (Box 2)
  - 2000 (Box 2)
  - 2001 (Box 2)
  - 2002 (Box 2)
  - 2003 (Box 2)
  - 2004 (Box 2)
  - 2005 (Box 2)
  - 2006 (Box 2)
  - 2007 (Box 2)
- Productions
  Records in the Productions series, 1995-2004 (.25 linear ft.), include production notes, bookings details, and scheduling for the Peter Sparling Dance Company's productions of the Four Seasons, Orfeo, and Peninsula
  - Four Seasons (Box 2)
  - Orfeo, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Peninsula, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Programs
  The Programs series, 1994-2007 (.25 linear feet), contains performance programs for the Peter Sparling Dance Company and productions by students at the Dance Gallery Studio. Programs in this series also includes productions for which Sparling did the choreography, but in which neither he nor his company performed.
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2000 (Box 3)
  - 2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002 (Box 3)
  - 2003 (Box 3)
  - 2004 (Box 3)
  - 2005 (Box 3)
  - 2006 (Box 3)
  - 2007 (Box 3)
- Promotional Materials
  The series, Promotional Materials, 1994-2007 (.25 linear ft.), includes press releases, media kits, posters, flyers, and postcards designed to provide information about the Peter Sparling Dance Company, the Dance Gallery Foundation, and the Dance Gallery Studio. The series includes oversized posters and photographs which are housed in an oversized box.
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2000 (Box 3)
  - 2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002 (Box 3)
  - 2004 (Box 3)
  - 2005 (Box 3)
  - 2006 (Box 3)
  - 2007 (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 3)
  - Oversize Material (Box 6)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  In the Audio-Visuals series, 1992-2007 (2.5 linear ft.) are photographs, on paper and compact discs, and video recordings, on VHS and DVD, of performances, rehearsals, and classes, as well as materials destined for use as promotional materials. The media in this series includes moving and still images from Aerial Web, Berliner Mass, children's workshops, Chronicle & Small Comforts, Diversion of Angels, El Penintente, Four Seasons, Jealousy, Johnny Angel, Les Parisiennes, New Bach, Orfeo, Peninsula, Philistines, Popular Songs, Port, Possible Dances, Seven Enigmas, Sonata, Traffic!, and Travelogue.
  - Photographs
    - Aerial Web (Box 3)
    - Berliner Mass (Box 3)
    - Children's Workshops (Box 3)
    - Chronicle & Small Comforts (Box 3)
    - Diversion of Angels (Box 3)
    - El Penitente (Box 3)
    - Four Seasons (Box 3)
    - Jealousy (Box 3)
    - Johnny Angel (Box 3)
    - Les Parisiennes (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - New Bach (Box 3)
    - Orfeo (Box 3)
    - Peninsula (Box 3)
    - Philistines (Box 3)
    - Popular Songs (Box 3)
    - Port (Box 3)
    - Possible Dances (Box 3)
    - Seven Enigmas (Box 3)
    - Sonata (Box 3)
    - Sparling, Peter (Box 3)
    - Traffic (Box 3)
    - Travelogue (Box 3)
  - CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery 2001, CD-R (Box 4)
    - PSDC April 2002, CD-R (Box 4)
    - PSDC Photos December 2002, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Raw Capture Degas/Peninsula Performance Network 2003, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Raw Capture Peninsula at Performance Network 2003, CD-R (Box 4)
    - DGS/PSDC Peninsula, Spring 2003, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Peninsula at Film Festival March 2004, 2 optical disks CD-Rs; CD-R (Box 4)
    - Peninsula Rehearsal June 23, 2004, 3 optical disks CD-Rs; CD-R (Box 4)
    - PSDC Pictures April 26, 2004, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Peninsula at Power Center June 2004, 3 optical disks CD-Rs; CD-R (Box 4)
    - Adult Modern Photos, Summer 2006, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery Photos June 21, 2006, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Newsletter Photos July 2006, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Fall 2006 Photos, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery undated, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Earle Photos undated, CD-R (Box 4)
    - PSDC undated, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Martin & Peter 4 Mac, CD-R (Box 4)
    - Dance Gallery Foundation Website Capture, CD-R (Box 4)
  - Videotapes
    - UMS Dance Program, Did You Know, Vol. 1 February, 2003, VHS (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling, Border Crossings April 6, 2000, VHS (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company in Peninsula, Power Center June 23, 2004, VHS (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company Repertory, Performance Network August 22, 2004, VHS (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company, Gluck's Orfeo ed Euridice, Educational Presentation April 11, 2001, VHS (Box 4)
    - MCACA Dance/New Works--Dance Gallery/Peter Sparling & Co., Sample of Work of Interpretive Artist April 24, 1997, VHS (Box 4)
    - Repertory Sampler--Dance Gallery/Peter Sparling & Co., VHS (Box 4)
    - Wildt St. Tom, VHS (Box 4)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company, www.Comnet.Org/DanceGallery, VHS (Box 4)
    - Comcast Newsmakers Peter Sparling TRT: 5 Minutes, VHS (Box 4)
    - 1. DGS Youth Repertory Group, Performance Network June 1, 2003, VHS (Box 5)
    - 2. PSDC, Katz Elementary March 18, 1997, VHS (Box 5)
    - 3. PSDC, Estabrook New Horizon February 4, 1997, VHS (Box 5)
    - 4. PSDC, Excerpts from Repertory, VHS (Box 5)
    - 5. PSDC, Hearts Plunder, VHS (Box 5)
    - 6. PSDC, Orfeo and Euridice, VHS (Box 5)
    - 7. PSDC, Orfeo ed Euridice, Michigan Theater, VHS (Box 5)
    - 8. UMS Presents PSDC, Orfeo ed Eurdice May 19, 2001, VHS (Box 5)
    - 9. PSDC, Berliner Mass/Seven Enigmas July 12, 1997 (Box 5)
    - 10. PSDC, General Promo Video, VHS (Box 5)
    - 11. PSDC, Peninsula May 13, 2003 (Box 5)
    - 12. BRAVO, Celebrating the Arts in Southeast Michigan, VHS (Box 5)
    - 13. Peter Sparling: Heidi Stoeckley, VHS (Box 5)
    - 14. PSDC, Excerpts from Repertory (Orfeo, Chronicles), VHS (Box 5)
    - 15. PSDC, Adventures in New Media July 10, 2000, VHS (Box 5)
    - 16. PSDC, Excerpts from Repertory, VHS (Box 5)
    - 17. PSDC, "Winter" from Vivaldi Four Seasons, VHS (Box 5)
    - 18. PSDC, Diversion of Angels/Chronicles, VHS (Box 5)
    - 19. DGS, The Wildt Street Space, VHS (Box 5)
    - 20. UMS Presents PSDC, The Orfeo ed Euridice Residency, VHS (Box 5)
    - 21. DGS, Bernie $ Dottie July 15, 2000, VHS (Box 5)
    - 22. PSDC, Traffic !/Possible Dances/Orfeo Suite January 11, 2001 (Box 5)
    - 23. PSDC, NEA Proposal FY 2001 Access/Dance, VHS (Box 5)
    - 24. DGS, Christina Sears, Girlstown Summer Camp 2002, VHS (Box 5)
    - 25. Peter Sparling, The Institute for Humanities, VHS (Box 5)
    - 26. PSDC & DGS, Promotional Video, VHS (Box 5)
    - 28. PSDC & DGS, Master GLPAA Promo Video, VHS (Box 5)
    - 29. PSDC & DGS, Repertory Sampler, VHS (Box 5)
    - 30. PSDC, "Move It" Dress Rehearsal June 24, 1992, VHS (Box 5)
    - 31. PSDC, Travelogue (excerpts), VHS (Box 5)
    - 32. PSDC, Promotional Video September 10, 1998 (Box 5)
    - 33. PSDC, "Possible Dances" (Box 5)
    - 34. DGS, Moscow Ballet Nutcracker/Kid's 2002, VHS (Box 5)
    - 35. DGS, Moscow Ballet/Kid's 2001, VHS (Box 5)
    - 36. DGS, Nutcracker/Academy of Dance Arts 2001-2002, VHS (Box 5)
    - 37. Peter Sparling, MCACA Samples of Work 1995, VHS (Box 5)
    - 38. DGS & Janet Lilly, Storybook, Michigan Theater, April 23, VHS (Box 5)
  - Digital Video Discs (DVDs)
    - Complete Peninsula, DVD-R (Box 5)
    - DGS/PSDC, Winter Wonderland, December 5 & 6 2003 (DVD Video) (Box 5)
    - Dance Gallery Studio, Spring Showcase, May 12 2002 (DVD Video) (Box 5)
    - Peter Sparling Dance Company, Promotional Video, Peninsula Part II, Les Parisiennes 2004, DVD-R (Box 5)
    - Peter Sparling, The End of Shame August 8, 2005, DVD-R (Box 5)
    - Peter Sparling, Odes (Studio Version) 2005, DVD-R (Box 5)
- Archived Website
  The Website series, 1998 (2 CD-Roms) includes screen captures of the Dance Gallery Foundation/Peter Sparling Dance Company website. The PSDC/DGF website includes information on the Foundation's activities, donor program, and internship opportunities; the Dance Gallery Studio's class schedules, fees, teacher profiles, and studio information; and the Peter Sparling Dance Company's schedule, repertory, events, company member profiles, mission statement, and educational outreach opportunities, as well as biographical information on Peter Sparling. The website capture included all information available on the core Dance Gallery Foundation website, but excluded content available on external websites, such as merchandise sold by Caf Press or class and company photographs offered for sale by Best Ever Media. The first website capture was done by Nancy Deromedi on July 9, 2008, and the second was done by Kate Donovan, using HTTrack, on December 16, 2008. The website address at the time of both captures was http://www.dancegalleryfoundation.org/.
  - Peter Sparling Dance Gallery Foundation Website Snapshots July 9, 2008, CD-R (Box 4)
  - Dance Gallery Foundation Website capture December 16, 2008, CD-R (Box 4)
Related Material
Researchers should note that related material on Peter Sparling can be found in the Peter Sparling Papers, also located at the Bentley Historical Library. This collection includes Sparling's personal papers, as well as materials on his dance training, performance, and teaching, including choreography notes and sketches, correspondence, clippings and reviews, programs, photographs, posters, and video and film of performances.